<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter id="telecom">
  <title>Telecom (SIP)</title>

  <para>Telecom support allows to build powerful converged VoIP applications
  by providing means for an application to handle/send SIP Messages. Note that
  Mobicents Sip Servlets is needed to be able to use this feature and that it
  is higly recommended to have knowledge about SIP and SIP Servlets 1.1 Java
  Specification to use it effectively.</para>

  <section>
    <title>Making phone calls</title>

    <para>To be able to initiate the setup of a call from your TorqueBox
    application here is what you need to do in your controller :</para>

    <para><example>
        <title>Code Excerpt to set up a call</title>

        <para><screen># get the sip factory from the servlet context
@sip_factory = $servlet_context.get_attribute('javax.servlet.sip.SipFactory')
puts @sip_factory

# create a new sip application session
@app_session = request.env['servlet_request'].get_session().get_application_session();

# create a new sip servlet request to start a call to the sip phone with from header equals to "sip:my_jruby_app_rocks@mobicents.org" and the to header equals to the sip_uri from the complaint variable
@sip_request = @sip_factory.create_request(@app_session, 'INVITE', 'sip:my_jruby_app_rocks@mobicents.org', @complaint.sip_uri);

# actually sending the request out to the sip phone
@sip_request.send();</screen></para>
      </example>This piece of code will create a SIP Request and send it out.
    But when the user will answer OK, you need to have some code to handle the
    response and this can be done by defining your own SIP controller</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Ruby Telco Classes</title>

    <para>In your Ruby or Rails application, all SIP classes should be placed
    under <filename>$RAILS_ROOT/app/sip/</filename>. No special naming
    convention is required, but the class name must match the path to the file
    containing it.</para>

    <informaltable>
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <thead>
          <row>
            <entry align="center">File name</entry>

            <entry align="center">Class name</entry>
          </row>
        </thead>

        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry><filename>$RAILS_ROOT/app/sip/telco_handler</filename></entry>

            <entry><type>SipHandler</type></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><filename>$RAILS_ROOT/app/sip/telco/handler</filename></entry>

            <entry><type>Telco::Handler</type></entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </informaltable>

    <para>Additionally, each Telco class must descend, at some point, from
    <type>TorqueBox::Sip::Base</type>.</para>

    <para><example>
        <title>SIP Telco class example
        (<filename>telco/handler.rb</filename>)</title>

        <para><screen>require 'torquebox/sip/base'
        module Telco
  class Handler &lt; TorqueBox::Sip::Base
    # Handle INVITE request to setup a call by answering 200 OK
    def do_invite(request) 
      request.create_response(200).send
    end
    
    # Handle BYE request to tear down a call by answering 200 OK
    def do_bye(request) 
      request.create_response(200).send
    end

    # Handle REGISTER request so that a SIP Phone can register with the application by answering 200 OK
    def do_register(request) 
      request.create_response(200).send
    end
 
    # Handle a successful response to an application initiated INVITE to set up a call (when a new complaint is filed throught the web part) by send an acknowledgment
    def do_success_response(response)
      response.create_ack.send
    end
  end
end</screen></para>
      </example></para>

    <para>Note that this is an example but the handler class can extend all
    the <methodname>do_<replaceable>XXX</replaceable></methodname> methods as
    defined per the Sip Servlets 1.1 Java Specification.</para>
  </section>
</chapter>
