<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter id="crypto">
  <title>Cryptography</title>

  <section id="crypto-key-stores">
    <title>Cryptographic Key Stores</title>

    <para>Cryptographic key stores may be configured for the application and
    used by any service requiring key material. Keystores themselves are
    encrypted to secure the key material itself.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Configure Key Stores: <filename>crypto.yml</filename></title>

    <para>A file named crypto.yml should contain a section for each keystore
    you wish to make available within your application.</para>

    <para>Each key store defined within <filename>crypto.yml</filename> must
    provide a path to the store, along with the password required to access
    the store.</para>

    <para><example>
        <title>Example <filename>crypto.yml</filename></title>

        <para><screen>truststore:
  store: truststore.jks
  password: foobar

keystore:
  store: keystore.jks
  password: foobar</screen></para>
      </example></para>

    <para>Each keystore is labelled with an identifier used to access it from
    other services. While any number of key stores may be configured with
    arbitrary identifiers, many services look for specific key stores by
    default.</para>

    <para>Some services, such as SOAP Endpoints attempt to use a key store
    named <classname>truststore</classname> if inbound signature verification
    is enabled. Likewise, the key store named <classname>keystore</classname>
    is the default for signing outbound responses.</para>

    <para>If the path to the keystore in the <parameter>store</parameter>
    parameter is an absolute path, it will be used as specified. If the path
    is relative, the application framework is responsible for defining those
    semantics.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Ruby-on-Rails and <filename>crypto.yml</filename></title>

      <para>To use cryptogrpahic key stores from your Ruby-on-Rails
      application, place crypto.yml in your application's
      <filename>config/</filename> directory. Relative paths to key stores
      specified in the store parameter are relative to the directory
      <filename><envar>$RAILS_ROOT</envar>/auth/</filename>.</para>

      <para><screen>RAILS_ROOT/
  config/
    crypto.yml
  auth/
    truststore.jks
    keystore.jks</screen></para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Managing Key Stores</title>

    <para>Key stores are kept in the Java Key Store format and managed using
    the <command>keytool</command> command-line utility that ships with the
    JDK.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Create a New Key Store</title>

      <para>When you generate or import your first key into the key store, it
      will be created as needed. The path to the key store is specified using
      the <option>-keystore</option> option.</para>

      <para><screen>$ keytool <emphasis>-keystore auth/keystore.jks</emphasis></screen>
      When a key store is first created while importing or generating a new
      key, you will be prompted to provide and verify the password to protect
      the entire keystore. This is the same password you provide through
      <filename>crypto.yml</filename>.</para>

      <para><screen>$ keytool -keystore auth/keystore.jks
<emphasis>Enter keystore password: 
Re-enter new password:</emphasis> </screen></para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Create a New Key Pair</title>

      <para>To create a new key pair to use for signing or encrypting
      functions, the <option>-genkey</option> option is used. The keytool
      utility will prompt you for several pieces of information. Each key is
      identified by an <emphasis>alias</emphasis>. By default -genkey attempts
      to create a key named <classname>mykey</classname>. The
      <option>-alias</option> option may be used to provide a different alias
      to register the key.</para>

      <para><screen>$ keytool -keystore truststore.jks <emphasis>-genkey -alias bobmcwhirter</emphasis> 
Enter keystore password:  
What is your first and last name?
  [Unknown]:  Bob McWhirter
What is the name of your organizational unit?
  [Unknown]:  TorqueBox
What is the name of your organization?
  [Unknown]:  JBoss
What is the name of your City or Locality?
  [Unknown]:  Wytheville
What is the name of your State or Province?
  [Unknown]:  Virginia
What is the two-letter country code for this unit?
  [Unknown]:  US
Is CN=Bob McWhirter, OU=TorqueBox, O=JBoss, L=Wytheville, ST=Virginia, C=US correct?
  [no]:  yes

Enter key password for &lt;bobmcwhirter&gt;
        (RETURN if same as keystore password):  
Re-enter new password:
$</screen></para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Inspect the Key Store</title>

      <para>The -list option may be used to list the contents of a key
      store.</para>

      <para><screen>$ keytool -keystore truststore.jks -list                      
Enter keystore password:  

Keystore type: JKS
Keystore provider: SUN

Your keystore contains 2 entries

<emphasis>bobmcwhirter</emphasis>, May 13, 2009, PrivateKeyEntry, 
Certificate fingerprint (MD5): E1:73:2B:34:26:80:CA:55:7C:E8:BC:C6:A2:F6:D0:10
<emphasis>mykey</emphasis>, May 13, 2009, PrivateKeyEntry, 
Certificate fingerprint (MD5): 24:3E:29:E2:6A:5F:AA:24:A2:F3:25:68:B6:6E:92:FF</screen></para>

      <para></para>

      <para></para>

      <para></para>
    </section>
  </section>
</chapter>
