<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter id="database">
  <title>Database Connectivity</title>

  <para>Typical applications require the use of databases. Within the Rails
  community, ActiveRecord is one of the more popular database connectivity
  libraries. With traditional Ruby-based applications, you needed to require
  the correct ActiveRecord adapter for the database you were connecting to.
  Each adapter managed the communication between the client and the end
  database, directly mediating the connection.</para>

  <para><mediaobject>
      <imageobject role="html">
        <imagedata align="center" fileref="images/database-traditional.png"
                   format="PNG" scale="70" />
      </imageobject>

      <imageobject role="fo">
        <imagedata align="center" fileref="images/database-traditional.svg"
                   format="SVG" scale="70" />
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject></para>

  <para>Since TorqueBox is based on the JBoss Java environment, it has the
  capability to use enterprise-grade JDBC (Java Database Connectivity API)
  drivers. Rails applications can take advantage of these drivers by using the
  generic ActiveRecord JDBC adapter. The adapter will locate and activate the
  correct underlying Java JDBC adapter for the target database.</para>

  <para><mediaobject>
      <imageobject role="html">
        <imagedata align="center" fileref="images/database-jdbc.png"
                   format="PNG" scale="70" />
      </imageobject>

      <imageobject role="fo">
        <imagedata align="center" fileref="images/database-jdbc.svg"
                   format="SVG" scale="70" />
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject></para>

  <para>The most visible change required of applications using the JDBC-based
  ActiveRecord adapter involves the gems your application must rely on.
  Primarily you must rely on the <code>activerecord-jdbc-adapter</code>. This
  adapter is adjusts ActiveRecord configuration to use the JDBC version of any
  specified driver.</para>

  <para>Additional gems need to be available to your system, depending on your
  target database:</para>

  <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
    <listitem>
      <para><filename>jdbc-postgres</filename></para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para><filename>jdbc-mysql</filename></para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para><filename>jdbc-sqlite3</filename></para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <para>These gems simply embody the Java JAR holding the actual underlying
  JDBC driver.</para>

  <para>No changes to your application's database configuration is required.
  You still specify the correct driver name for the database, such as
  <code>postgresql</code> or <code>sqlite3</code>.</para>
</chapter>
