<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter id="jboss">
  <title>JBoss AS Crash Course</title>

  <para>
    The JBoss Application Server (AS6) is the foundation upon which
    TorqueBox is built.  You can go a long way with TorqueBox without
    knowing anything about the administration of JBoss AS, but for
    advanced applications, it's worth knowing something about how AS
    is configured and extended.  Feel free to skip this section if
    you're just getting started with TorqueBox, and use it as a
    reference later.
  </para>

  <section>
    <title>Configuring</title>
    <para>
      JBoss has a very simple way of representing server
      configurations.  Each directory beneath
      <filename>server/</filename> denotes a single configuration
      <emphasis>profile</emphasis>.
    </para>
    <para><mediaobject>
      <imageobject >
        <imagedata align="center" fileref="images/jboss-server.png"
                   format="PNG" />
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject></para>
    <para>
      TorqueBox provides two: <emphasis>default</emphasis> and
      <emphasis>all</emphasis>.  A stock JBoss distribution will come
      with others, as you see above, and of course you're free to
      create your own custom profiles.
    </para>
    <para>
      Some libraries and config files are common to all server
      configurations.  To conserve disk space, these are kept in the
      <filename>common/</filename> directory.  This is, in fact, where
      the TorqueBox deployers reside.
    </para>

    <para>
      All configuration profiles have a common structure, and usually
      include the following directories: <filename>conf/</filename>,
      <filename>lib/</filename>, <filename>deployers/</filename>, and
      <filename>deploy/</filename>.  In general, it isn't a good idea
      to remove anything from these directories that you didn't put
      there yourself.
    </para>
    <para><mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata align="center" fileref="images/jboss-default.png"
                   format="PNG" />
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject></para>
    <para>
      In addition, some directories are created automatically at
      runtime, as needed: <filename>tmp/</filename>,
      <filename>work/</filename>, <filename>data/</filename>, and
      <filename>log/</filename>.  Though not typically necessary, you
      may safely delete these when the server is not running to clear
      its persistent state.
    </para>

  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Running</title>
    <para>
      The <filename>$JBOSS_HOME/bin/</filename> directory contains the main JBoss
      entry point, <filename>run.sh</filename> (or
      <filename>run.bat</filename>), along with its config file,
      <filename>run.conf</filename>.  Running the JBoss server is
      simple:

      <screen> <prompt>$</prompt> <command>$JBOSS_HOME/bin/run.sh</command> </screen>

      By default, the <filename>default</filename> configuration
      profile is used.  Use the <option>-c</option> option to specify
      a different configuration.  For example, to put JBoss in
      "clustered" mode:

      <screen> <prompt>$</prompt> <command>$JBOSS_HOME/bin/run.sh -c all</command> </screen>

      You may set Java system properties using the <option>-D</option>
      option.  Pass <option>-h</option> for a list of all the
      available options.
    </para>
    <para>
      Permanent runtime configuration of JBoss should go in
      <filename>bin/run.conf</filename>. For example, your application
      may require more memory (RAM) than the default allocated. Edit
      <filename>run.conf</filename> to increase the value of
      <option>-Xmx</option> to something reasonable.
    </para>
    <para>
      Though <xref linkend="capistrano-support" /> doesn't strictly
      require it, in production you may prefer to control JBoss via a
      Unix "init script", examples of which may be found in
      <filename>bin/</filename>.  Feel free to tweak one for your
      particular OS.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Deploying</title>
    <para>
      Each server configuration has a <filename>deploy/</filename>
      subdirectory, the contents of which determine the applications
      and services JBoss runs.  These apps and services are
      represented as archives, "exploded" folders, or text files
      called "deployment descriptors".  JBoss constantly monitors
      changes to this directory, hot-deploying an artifact when it's
      added, undeploying it when it's removed, and "bouncing"
      (redeploying) it when it's changed.
    </para>
    <para><mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata align="center" fileref="images/jboss-deploy.png"
                   format="PNG" scale="70" />
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject></para>
    <para>
      The <filename>deploy/</filename> directory is searched
      recursively, so you can create whatever directory structure you
      need beneath it to isolate your artifacts from the stock JBoss
      ones.
    </para>
    <para>
      TorqueBox provides Rake tasks to create and copy a deployment
      descriptor for your Ruby application to
      <filename>deploy/</filename>.  For more details, see <xref
      linkend="deployment" /> and <xref linkend="deployment-descriptors" />.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Logging</title>
    <para>
      Each server configuration has a <filename>log/</filename>
      subdirectory (created at runtime, if necessary) that contains
      the log messages generated by JBoss as determined by its
      configuration.
    </para>
    <para>
      JBoss provides a very sophisticated logging system that nobody
      completely understands.  Logging configuration rules are
      contained in <filename>deploy/jboss-logging.xml</filename>, in
      which may be found example configs for categorized log message
      routing, complex file rotation, syslog integration, SMTP
      notifications, SNMP traps, JMS, JMX and more!  It is
      <emphasis>WAY</emphasis> beyond the scope of this document to
      explain those rules, but by default you will see INFO messages
      on the console (the shell where you start JBoss) and
      persistently written to <filename>log/server.log</filename>.
      You can control the log level easily using the following system
      property:

      <screen> <prompt>$</prompt> <command>$JBOSS_HOME/bin/run.sh -Djboss.server.log.threshold=DEBUG</command> </screen>

      Any messages written to <constant>stdout</constant> or
      <constant>stderr</constant> will also be displayed on the
      console and written to <filename>log/server.log</filename>.
    </para>
    
    <section>
      <title>The <classname>TorqueBox::Logger</classname></title>
      <para>
        Ruby Loggers work normally inside of TorqueBox, of course, and
        you'll find your Rails log files exactly where you expect them
        to be.  But some users, especially those already familiar with
        JBoss logging, may prefer for their Ruby log messages to be
        passed to JBoss.  This is easily achieved using the
        <classname>TorqueBox::Logger</classname>, constructed with an
        optional "category".  For example, you may configure your
        Rails app like so:

        <screen> <code>config.logger = TorqueBox::Logger.new</code> </screen>

        This results in all Rails-generated log messages passed to
        JBoss, hence written to <filename>log/server.log</filename> in
        the default configuration.  The category for these messages
        will be the application's name.  You can override this by
        passing the category name in the constructor:

        <screen> <code>TorqueBox::Logger.new( "Billing" )</code> </screen>

        You can also pass a class in the constructor, as is common in Java applications:

        <screen> <code>@logger = TorqueBox::Logger.new( self.class )</code> </screen>

        This allows you to be more strategic with your logging,
        sending some messages to the normal Rails logs and others to
        JBoss for more "enterprisey" processing.

      </para>
    </section>

  </section>

</chapter>
