<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter id="rails2">
  <title>Ruby on Rails</title>

  <section id="rails-support">
    <title><productname>Ruby on Rails</productname> Applications</title>

    <para>Ruby-on-Rails (also referred to as "RoR" or "Rails") is one of the
    most popular Model-View-Controller (MVC) frameworks for the Ruby language.
    It was originally created by David Heinemeier Hansson at <ulink
    url="http://37signals.com/">37signals</ulink> during the course of
    building many actual Ruby applications for their consulting
    business.</para>

    <para>Rails has straight-forward components representing models, views,
    and controllers. The framework as a whole values convention over
    configuration. It has been described as "opinionated software" in that
    many decisions have been taken away from the end-user.</para>

    <para>It is exactly the opinionated nature of Rails that allows it to be
    considered a simple and agile framework for quickly building web-based
    applications. Additionally, since Ruby is an interpreted language instead
    of compiled, the assets of an application can be edited quickly, with the
    results being immediately available. In most cases, the application does
    not need to be restarted to see changes in models, views or controllers
    reflected.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Rails 2.3.x versus 3.x</title>

    <para>TorqueBox supports both the 2.3.x and 3.x codelines of Rails. By
    default, all utilities prefer the latest version of a given gem, which in
    the current case is ${version.rails3}.</para>

    <para>To specify a specific version of utilities such as the rails command
    used to create applications, simply specify the version number between
    underscores immediately following the command name.</para>

    <informalexample>
      <para><screen>$ rails _${version.rails2}_ myapp</screen></para>
    </informalexample>
  </section>

  <section id="preparing-your-rails-application">
    <title>Preparing your Rails application</title>

    <para>While TorqueBox is 100% compatible with Ruby-on-Rails, there are a
    few steps that must be taken to ensure success. The biggest issues to
    contend with involve database access and native gems. The distribution
    includes a Rails application template to make the creation or adaptation
    of a codebase to TorqueBox easier.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Using the application template</title>

      <para>You can use the included application template to setup a new Rails
      application or modify an existing one to work with TorqueBox.</para>

      <section>
        <title>Creating a new Rails application</title>

        <para>To create a new Rails application using the template, simply use
        the <parameter>-m</parameter> parameter when you execute the
        <command>rails</command> command.</para>

        <formalpara>
          <title>Rails 2.3.x</title>

          <para><screen><prompt>$</prompt> <command>rails</command> <parameter>_${version.rails2}_ myapp -m <envar>$TORQUEBOX_HOME</envar>/share/rails/template.rb</parameter></screen></para>
        </formalpara>

        <formalpara>
          <title>Rails 3.x</title>

          <para><screen><prompt>$</prompt> <command>rails</command> new <parameter>myapp -m <envar>$TORQUEBOX_HOME</envar>/share/rails/template.rb</parameter></screen></para>
        </formalpara>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Applying template to an existing application</title>

        <para>To apply the template to an existing application, simply use the
        <command>rails:template</command> rake task.</para>

        <para><screen><prompt>$</prompt> <command>rake</command> <parameter>rails:template</parameter> <varname>LOCATION</varname>=<envar>$TORQUEBOX_HOME</envar>/share/rails/template.rb</screen></para>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Manually configuring an application</title>

      <section>
        <title>Include the JDBC Gems for Database Connectivity</title>

        <para>ActiveRecord applications deployed on TorqueBox benefit from
        using the Java-based JDBC database drivers. These drivers are provided
        as a handful of gems which you may include into your application
        through <filename>config/environment.rb</filename> or a
        <filename>Gemfile</filename>. For more information on database
        connectivity wihtin the TorqueBox environment, please see <xref
        linkend="database" />. Database gems supporting MySQL, PostgreSQL, and
        SQLite3 are supplied in the TorqueBox binary distribution.</para>

        <formalpara>
          <title>Rails 2.x</title>

          <para>You simply must reference the
          <filename>activerecord-jdbc-adapter</filename> from your
          <filename>environment.rb</filename> within the
          <code>Rails::Initializer.run</code> block.</para>
        </formalpara>

        <para><programlisting>Rails::Initializer.run do |config|

<emphasis>  config.gem "activerecord-jdbc-adapter",
             :require=&gt;'jdbc_adapter'
</emphasis>
end</programlisting></para>

        <para>All databases will require inclusion of the
        <filename>activerecord-jdbc-adapter</filename>. No other gems need to
        be required or loaded, since ActiveRecord will perform further
        discovery on its own. </para>

        <formalpara>
          <title>Rails 3.x</title>

          <para>Rails 3 uses bundler to manage the dependencies of your
          application. To specify the requirement of the
          <filename>activerecord-jdbc-adapter</filename> with Rails 3, simple
          add it to your <filename>Gemfile</filename>. Additionally, any
          specific JDBC driver your application will require should be
          indicated.</para>
        </formalpara>

        <para><informalexample>
            <para><programlisting>gem 'activerecord-jdbc-adapter'
gem 'jdbc-sqlite3'</programlisting></para>
          </informalexample></para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Eliminate or replace "native" Gems</title>

        <para>"Native" gems that rely upon machine-specific compiled code do
        not function with JRuby and TorqueBox. You must replaced these gems
        with pure-Ruby or pure-Java implementations. Some native gems using
        FFI are usable within TorqueBox.</para>
      </section>
    </section>
  </section>
</chapter>
